Arduinos!
I'm going to talk about what they are, what
they can do, and the basics of how to set
one up to do simple things like make an LED
dimming circuit, control the speed of motors,
and even make a simple oscilloscope.
So what is an Arduino?
I'm sure you've heard about these things a
million times by now, and if you are confused
you have every right to be, because the word
Arduino refers to so many different things.
Keep watching and I will explain all of them.
Microcontrollers are integrated circuits that
are basically tiny computers.
They can run small, simple software programs.
They are low powered enough that they can
be powered by a battery for days, but they
are fast enough to process data much faster
than any human being can think.
Arduino is a company in Italy that designs
and sells circuit boards that make microcontrollers
easy to use.
They call these circuit boards Arduinos, and
there are a lot of different types of Arduinos!
For example, you've got simple Arduino boards
like the Arduino Uno, which is cheap and good
enough for most projects.
You could use an Arduino Uno to control motors,
lighting, cameras, or even build a simple
robot.
And then you have more fancy Arduinos with
more powerful processors which have wifi,
ethernet and more.
The company Arduino open sources all of their
hardware designs, which means that you don't
just have to buy from them, there are countless
3rd party companies that make their own variants
of the Arduino hardware designs.
They can't call them Arduinos, but functionally
they are the same thing.
There are also these things called Arduino
"shields", which are basically circuit boards
that plug into your main Arduino circuit board,
and let you do more stuff.
For example, Adafruit makes shields that let
you control motors and servos, without having
to design motor control circuitry.
And Sparkfun have shields that let you turn
your Arduino into a simple cell phone, or
an MP3 player!
Okay, so that was a quick overview of Arduino
the company, and Arduino hardware.
But there's more!
There's also the Arduino software development
environment, and this is what makes Arduino
good for beginners.
Historically, if you wanted to program microcontrollers,
you'd have to type out a lot of binary and
memorize a lot of hard to remember registers
and instructions.
Then you'd have to use special programming
hardware with custom made cables to upload
your program onto your microcontroller.
Arduino, the company, got rid of all of that.
They created software that works on Windows,
Mac, and Linux, which makes uploading your
code as simple as connecting a USB cable and
clicking a button.
They created a programming language that lets
you configure all of the Arduino hardware
products in the same way.
And although it's not as simple as learning
Python, the Arduino software is one of the
easiest programming experiences you'll ever
have.
Ok, so hopefully that clarifies what Arduino
means in different contexts.
Now when people say they used "an Arduino"
for their project, they are probably talking
about the Arduino Uno.
It's highly unlikely that you will outgrow
one any time soon, so it's the perfect Arduino
hardware for this beginners tutorial.
You can get them from Amazon cheaply, and
if you have the money I recommend buying one
of the many Uno kits out there where you get
a lot of different pieces of hardware to play
with.
Okay, so you've got your Arduino Uno.
The first thing I want to do is get you familiar
with the hardware.
You will often hear Arduinos being called
microcontrollers, and that's technically incorrect.
Arduinos are circuit boards that have microcontroller
chips on them, but they also have a lot of
other stuff on there too.
Let's take a quick tour.
This is the microcontroller.
Arduino UNOs use a series of microcontrollers
called ATMEGA AVRs.
They are made by a company called Atmel.
You can buy just the bare chips on their own
for about a dollar but then you'd have to
do a lot of soldering.
Connected to the microcontroller is a crystal
resonator.
This controls how fast the microcontroller
is running.
I have a separate tutorial on resonators and
oscillators which you might find useful.
Now in order to upload the software you create
to the main microcontroller, there's actually
another microcontroller!
This chip is what lets you connect your USB
cable to the Arduino board, and communicate
via USB.
It lets you upload your programs onto the
main microcontroller, and once you have your
program running, this chip is what allows
you to send messages back and forth between
your computer and your Arduino.
And this is extremely important for debugging!
One great thing about Arduinos is that you
can power them purely from your USB cable.
But!
If you don't want your project always attached
to a computer, you can just use an external
9 volt DC power source with the barrel jack
over here.
The Uno has a built in voltage regulator that
will reduce the voltage to 5 volts.
And if you ever want to "reboot" your Arduino's
program, you've got a reset button.
If you have time, it's worth studying the
Arduino Uno schematic.
Don't worry if it looks complicated, you don't
need to understand most of it, I'm trying
to get you to understand what the Arduino
designers did.
They took an off the shelf microcontroller
that requires a lot of extra parts to get
working, and they put all of those things
together in an easy to use way.
And if you choose to learn more about electronics,
you can create circuit boards like this too.
Okay, so that's what's under the hood.
Next let's talk about the pin connectors.
Over here you have the power pins.
If you want, you can connect wires here to
power other circuitry with 5 volts or 3.3
volts.
Just make sure you whatever you power doesn't
draw more than a few milliamps!
A few LEDs is okay, but a large motor would
be an Ardui-nono.
(Boo!
You suck!)
TX and RX is for sending and receiving serial
data.
You could use this port to send and receive
data from a GPS module, bluetooth modules,
wifi modules and more.
Pins 2 to 13 are for digital inputs and outputs.
Normally when people think of binary you think
of just spitting out 0s and 1s.
But!
With most microcontroller pins you can actually
activate a third state, and use them as a
digital input.
So you can use this pin as an output where
it spits out 5V for a digital 1, or 0V for
a digital 0.
Or, you can internally configure the Arduino
to expect a voltage on the pin, and that voltage
could be interpreted as a 1 or a 0.
It's a system called tristate logic, and it's
worth reading up on, but Arduino makes it
really easy to change between inputs and outputs
in software.
Here we have 6 analog input pins, and these
are used to measure continuous voltages anywhere
from 0 to 5V.
I'll talk more about this later in the video.
Finally some of the pins have a tilde in front
of them, and this means that you can use them
to output pulse width modulated square waves,
which I will also show later in the video.
Okay enough about the hardware.
Most of the work you do with your Arduino
will actually be in the software.
So start out by downloading the Arduino software
from arduino.cc.
During the installation you can expect a lot
of prompts like this to show up, where you
are asked if you want to install various drivers.
Just say yes to everything.
Once you are done, connect the Arduino to
your computer with a USB cable.
Next, start up the Arduino development environment.
The first thing you want to do is make sure
that the software tries to connect to the
right type of Arduino.
Go to Tools, Boards, and we are going to be
using an Arduino Uno.
Next we have to make sure the Arduino environment
can actually connect and communicate with
your Arduino.
Go to Tools, Ports, and select the COM or
serial port where your Arduino is connected.
If there isn't an Arduino listed here, you
may have a problem with your drivers, or you
can try plugging your Arduino into a different
USB port.
The Arduino software has a ton of fantastic,
easy to follow demo programs, and studying
these is the best place to start learning
how to code.
Arduino calls them "sketches" which is just
a fancy name for a program that you upload
to your Arduino.
Let's start with an example where we measure
voltages that are being fed into the Arduino.
Go to File, Examples, Basics, AnalogReadSerial.
All the Arduino examples contain instructions
on how to set up the hardware.
This one is telling us "Attach the center
pin of a potentiometer to pin A0, and the
outside pins to +5V and ground."
Okay... let's do that!
A 1k or a 10k potentiometer will work great
for this.
We are going to be using it as a voltage divider
to create a voltage anywhere from 0 to 5 volts.
Make sure you've watched my voltage divider
tutorial if you don't understand how that
works.
Every Arduino program will have two main areas,
the setup and the loop.
The setup area is where you configure your
Arduino to do certain things for the duration
of your program.
It could be information on which pins are
inputs, and which are outputs, but in this
case we are telling it to send serial data
to our computer at 9600 bits per second, which
is a pretty standard data rate for these situations.
The loop is the area of code that repeats
over and over again for as long as the Arduino
has power to it.
This line will measure the voltage on pin
A0, and store the value of it in a temporary
place in memory that we are calling sensorValue.
sensorValue is an int, or integer, meaning
it is a whole number.
Once we have copied the analog voltage reading
to sensorValue, the command Serial.println
will transmit that value from our Arduino,
through the USB cable, to our computer, and
we can view it.
Click Upload, it will compile the sketch and
upload it to your Arduino.
Hit the reset button.
Now go to Tools, Serial Monitor.
You should see a bunch of numbers flying by.
As you vary the potentiometer from 0 to 5
volts, you should see a number on screen from
0 to 1023.
This is because internally, the Arduino represents
the analog voltages it measures with a 10
bit number which can be from 0 to 1023.
The number scales linearly with the voltage,
so 2.5 volts would be halfway down at 512.
You can use these formulas to convert from
analog tick values to real world voltages,
and vice versa.
Now close the serial monitor, and go to Tools,
Serial plotter.
Now you can get a graph of the voltage your
potentiometer is creating over time.
It's basically a very simple, low bandwidth
oscilloscope!
Let's try another experiment where we build
a simple LED dimmer.
Go to File, Examples, Analog, AnalogInOutSerial.
The instructions for the potentiometer are
the same as before.
It also says to connect an LED from digital
pin 9, to ground.
Note that it is implied that you will put
a resistor in series with the LED!
The pins on an Arduino cannot supply much
current.
Any more than about 20mA and you risk permanently
destroying that pin.
I have detailed tutorials on LEDs and resistor
values, but for now let's just use a 1k resistor
attached to ground.
The other side goes to the cathode of an LED,
and the LED's anode goes to pin 9.
We've already talked about what an int is,
but this const int means that the label analogOutPin
will always translate to the number 9 throughout
the rest of the program.
For example here, saying analogWrite(9, outputvalue)
wouldn't be very clear.
Like... what the hell is the 9 for?
Instead we are declaring analogOutPin to be
a place in the Arduino's memory that always
stores the constant, fixed number 9, so when
we write other pieces of code we don't have
to memorize which pin numbers we are using
for different things.
It's not a big deal right now but this becomes
more important when have programs that use
a lot of different pins.
sensorValue and outputValue are non-constant
integer numbers, which means they can change
value during the operation of the program.
The term for this in programming is a "variable".
On the Arduino platform, an int variable can
hold a number anywhere between -32,768 and
+32,767.
The setup is the same as before, and once
again we are using the analogRead function
to measure the voltage on a certain pin, which
turns out to be pin A0.
We store that value in sensorValue.
Now we know that the Arduino internally represents
analog voltages with numbers from 0 to 1023,
but the analogWrite function only accepts
values from 0 to 255.
So we use the map function here to linearly
scale sensorValue down to values between 0
and 255.
Then the analogWrite function takes the number
stored in outputValue and uses it to control
the voltage on analogOutPin, which is in fact
pin number 9.
The serial printing stuff is similar to what
we had before, and at the end of each loop
the delay function will make the Arduino pause
execution of all code for a specific number
of milliseconds.
Once again we click upload, hit reset on the
Arduino, and now we have a system that can
control the brightness of an LED with a potentiometer!
Now you are probably thinking... so what?
You can do that without the Arduino!
Well, let's probe the output of pin 9 with
an oscilloscope to see what's really happening
here.
We've got a pulse width modulated square wave!
We can control it with the potentiometer,
and it's very precise.
Now, instead of an LED, let's control something
else.
Let's take this part of the circuit from my
classic pulse width modulation tutorial, and
now we will be able to control a motor digitally,
instead of a sometimes glitchy 555 circuit.
So you might be thinking that it's weird that
an Arduino function called analogWrite is
in fact controlling a pulse width modulated
square wave.
Well, the idea is that you would use an RC
low pass filter to convert that square wave
into a continuous analog voltage, and I have
separate tutorials on how to do this.
Once you have looked at a few examples and
understand how they work, you can delete pieces
of code, and modify existing pieces of code
to create whatever you want.
Here I've gotten rid of the potentiometer
control and serial stuff, and I created a
loop that turns a motor off for 1 second,
turns the motor on at 50% speed for one second,
then it goes full speed for 1 second.
So you can see how by reading voltages from
sensors, and writing code to control motors
and servos, an Arduino can easily become the
brains of a simple robot.
In fact, you can get kits to build Arduino
based robots for as little as $74.
So those were two easy examples of what you
can do with an Arduino, but you can do SO
much more, and there are tutorials all over
the internet for them.
Thank you for watching, and if you found this
video useful, please check out my sponsor
Audible.
Audible is a company owned by Amazon and basically
they have a huge selection of audiobooks that
you can buy and listen to on the way to work
or when you're at the gym.
They've got a promotion right now where you
can get a free audiobook if you sign up for
their free 30 day trial by visiting audible.com/afrotechmods
Once you're there, you can log in with your
existing Amazon account.
You need to give them a credit card number
but you can cancel your free trial at any
time, and you still get to keep the free audiobook.
I personally like Ryan Holiday - he's got
this amazing book called Trust Me, I'm Lying:
Confessions of a Media Manipulator.
He's got these crazy stories about how anyone
can pose as a fake "expert" and get quoted
in news articles.
Once you pick out your free audiobook, you
download the Audible app on your phone or
tablet, and you can access your audiobooks
from anywhere.
If that sounds interesting to you, click on
the link in the video description section
or visit audible.com/afrotechmods to start
your free trial!